Guide to the Rice Institute Business Manager papers, 1874-1951 UA 353
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice Institute Business Manager's papers, 1874-1951
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 353
40 Linear Feet (46 boxes)
This collection documents not only the early years of the Rice Institute, but also the years the institute was in the planning stages and William Marsh Rice's involvement. The assets of the institute are also detailed.
Biographical / Historical
This collection documents not only the early years of the Rice Institute, but also the years the institute was in the planning stages and William Marsh Rice's involvement. The assets of the institute are also detailed.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents not only the early years of the Rice Institute, but also the years the institute was in the planning stages and William Marsh Rice's involvement. The assets of the institute are also detailed.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection resided in the President's Office and was maintained by Carl MacDowell, Assistant to the President, 1976-1999. The materials were transferred to the archives in the early 2000s.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Rice University--History; Business
Document Types
Correspondence; reports; minutes (administrative records)
- Series I: President
  - 1908-1910 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1911-1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1915-1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Residence
    - 1910-1911 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1912-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Travel
    - 1917-1923 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1924-1929 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1930-1936 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Series II: Fellowships, Funds, and Scholarships
  - Alumni Endowment Fund, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Samuel Fain Carter Fellowship, 1932-1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - George S. Cohen Endowment Fund, 1936-1938 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Lady Geddes Prize Fund, 1924-1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Godwin Lectureship, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Music Lectureship, 1923-1932 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Owen Wister Literary Society Fund, 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Physical Education Fund, 1930-1935 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Physical Education Fund, 1934-1938 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Student Loan Fund, 1923-1937 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Raymond R. Stone Mechanical Engineering Fund, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sara Stratford Fund for Women, 1931-1938 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Texaco Development Corporation Fellowship, 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Traveling Fellowship in Architecture, 1928-1932 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Pallas Athene Literary Society scholarships, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Elizabeth Baldwin Literary Society Scholarship, 1927-1930 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Thomas & Pauline Martin Dickson Scholarship, 1934-1937 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - T.R. & Julia Hadley Franklin Scholarship Fund, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Friends of Rice scholarships, 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Katie B. Howard Scholarship, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Daniel Ripley Scholarship, 1928-1931 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Edith Ripley Scholarship, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sharp Lectureship & Scholarship Fund, 1925-1938 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Ellen Axson Wilson Scholarship, 1922-1937 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Scholarships, general, 1920-1938 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series III: Correspondence
  - William Marsh Rice Family
    - WMR from Frederick Allyn Rice, 1874-1886 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - WMR from Frederick Allyn Rice, 1897-1900 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - WMR from William M. Rice, Jr., 1897-1899 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - WMR from Minerva Rice Olds, 1896-1897 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - WMR from Benjamin Botts Rice (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - William M. Rice, Jr. from WMR, 1895-1899 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - General, 1896-1901 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Business
    - WMR from Charles Adams (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - WMR from James Baker, Jr., 1897-1898 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - WMR from Baker, Botts, Baker & Lovett, 1896-1898 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - WMR from C.P.Benson, 1897-1899 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - WMR from Philip Carson, 1897-1898 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - WMR from J.L. Clark, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - WMR from W.D. Cleveland, 1897-1899 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - WMR from A.B. Cohn, 1896-1897 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - WMR from A.B. Cohn, 1898 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - WMR from A.B. Cohn, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - WMR from James & Ben P. Converse, 1896-1899 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - WMR from A.B. Doucette, 1898-1899 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - WMR from W.J. Finks & A.T. Gordon, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - WMR from Forest Home Cemetery, 1897 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - WMR from P.M. Granberry, 1897-1899 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - WMR from Houston Ice & Brewing Co., 1897-1899 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - WMR to and from N. Mackey, 1897-1899 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - WMR from J.E. McAshan (South Texas National Bank), 1896-1900 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - WMR from Merchants & Planters Oil Co., 1896-1899 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - WMR from W.L. Moody, 1890-1899 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - WMR from George L. Porter, 1897-1898 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - WMR from E.D. Pruett, 1898-1899 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - WMR from Lawson Purdy, 1900 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - WMR from A.T. Randolph, 1897-1899 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - WMR from E. Raphael, 1897-1898 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - WMR from W.W. Reid (First National Bank, Orange, TX), 1896-1899 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - WMR & E. Raphael from W.G. Rucker, 1898-1899 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - WMR from Charles O. Smith, 1896 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - WMR from G.W. Smyth (Sabine Tram Co.), 1897-1898 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - WMR from John Steiner, 1897-1898 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - WMR from R.B. Stephens, 1897-1898 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - WMR from J.B. Summerfield, 1899 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - WMR fromThomson & Donnan, 1896-1899 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - WMR from P.B. Timson (Houston Land & Trust Co.), 1898-1899 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - WMR from Ruth A. Watrous, 1897-1898 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - General to WMR & F.A. Rice, 1890-1897 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - General to and from WMR, 1898-1900 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Capt. James Baker, Jr. from WMR, 1896-1898, 1900 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - A.B. Cohn from WMR, 1897 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - B.P. Converse from WMR, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - George E. Dickey from WMR, 1893-1894 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - B.F. Dupree from WMR, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Uriah Lott from WMR, 1898 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - W.G. Rucker from WMR, 1894 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - To Baker, Botts, Baker & Lovett from various, 1896-1900 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - A.B. Cohn from James A. Baker, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - A.B. Cohn from J.S. Rice, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - A.B. Cohn from W.G.Rucker, 1899 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - A.B. Cohn from W.B. Springfield, 1898 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - To James A. Baker from various, 1897-1898 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - General, 1892-1903 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Financial
  - Credits, statements, correspondence, bank book
    - Bank account credits, South Texas Naitonal Bank, 1896-1899 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Account credits, First National Bank of Houston, 1899 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Bank statements & correspondence, South Texas National Bank, 1897-1899 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Bank statements & deposits, Houston Brick Works, 1897-1899 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Bank statements, First National Bank of Houston, 1897-1900 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Bank book, First National Bank of Houston, 1901-1904 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - WMR tax value statements & correspondence, 1880-1900 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - S.M. Swenson & Sons statements & correspondence, 1892-1899 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - W.G. Rucker land survey statements, 1894-1900 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - James Converse tax account statements for M/M WMR, 1895-1900 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Houston Brick Works payroll, tax assessments, comparative statements, 1896-1899 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Galveston Wharf Co. statements of receipts & expenditures, 1896-1899 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Various financial correspondence & statements, 1895-1900 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Financial receipts & correspondence, 1896-1911 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Promissory notes, 1881-1903 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Financial reports, 1898-1934 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Mackey property accounting of utilities paid, 1897-1899 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Bank books, 1902-1908 (Box 9, Envelope 12)
    - J.S. Rice & WMR Lumber statements & correspondence, 1897-1899 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - General
    - Alcohol bond, 1918-1925 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - [RIce] Athletic Association, 1917-1924 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - [Rice] Athletic Association football broadcasts, 1927-1935 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Autry House, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Bonds, 1936-1937 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Budget, 1913-1931 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Budget, 1914-1927 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Budget, 1932-1938 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Budgets & appropriations, 1916-1928 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, general, 1911-1930 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, general, 1923-1931 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, general, 1931-1938 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Cram, Goodhue & Ferguson, 1910 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - H.R. Cullen oil leases, 1923-1928 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - H.R. Cullen oil leases, Pierce Junction, 1927-1929 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Delivery car taxes, 1917 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Faculty enlistment in Army, 1917-1918 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Grounds improvement estimate, 1912 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - 1925-1937 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Girl Scout Council, 1923 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Mike Hogg loan correspondence, 1917, 1934-1935 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Income tax, 1913-1925 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Income tax, 1926-1938 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Insurance, 1914-1932 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Insurance claims, 1916-1917, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 15)
    - Jesse Jones renewal of loan, 1916-1920 (Box 11, Folder 16)
    - John H. Kirby, 1916-1917 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - H. Masterson/N.T. Masterson renewal of loans, 1916-1919 (Box 11, Folder 18)
    - Merchants & Planters Oil Co., 1914-1919 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Natural gas service, Power House, 1926-1927 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Library, 1941 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Oil paintings (portraits), 1908-1911 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Payments, Institute, 1922-1923 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Requests for payments, Institute buildings, 1911-1912 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - H.B. Rice, 1914-1917 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - F.A. Rice & WMR stock certificates, 1886-1901 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Salaries, 1912-1918 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Salaries, 1921-1928 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Steam boilers, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Timber estimates, Jasper County, 1911 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Water connections with City of Houston, 1911, 1920-21 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Water service, Ye Olde College Inn & Hermann Park, 1920-1923 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Estate settlements
    - William Marsh Rice
      - Documents, correspondence, 1900-1901 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Documents, correspondence, 1902-1904 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - Documents, correspondence, 1905-1910 (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Opinions, correspondence, 1902-1903 (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Inheritance taxes, 1905-1916 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Exhibits, A-Q, 1906 (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - Exhibits, R-Z, 1906 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - Elizabeth B. Rice, 1897 (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - WMR & Elizabeth B. Rice, Louisiana lands, 1900-1907 (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - WMR & Elizabeth B. Rice, Louisiana lands, 1908-1910 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - William M. Rice, Jr.
      - Settlement, 1943-1948 (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - Accounts, Houston Bank & Trust, 1944-1947 (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Crawford St. house, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Englewood Dev. Co. stock, 1944-1951 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - First Presbyterian Church, 1947 (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Parkway Dev. Co., 1946-1949 (Box 14, Folder 8)
      - Houston Ship Channel Improvement Co., 1948 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - J.S. Rice
      - Inventory, 1928-1932 (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - WMR & J.S. Rice Agency Trust statements, Houston Bank & Trust Co., 1947-1953 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - WMR & J.S. Rice Lumber Co., 1944-1945 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Minerva Rice Olds, 1908-1909 (Box 14, Folder 13)
- Series V: Property
  - Correspondence, 1897-1922 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Inventory, Harris County, 1879-1898 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Inventory, Texas, 1887-1898 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Houston Ship Channel, 1928-1943 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - San Antonio & Aransas Pass Railway Co. spur track, 1913-1914 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Southgate, Inc., 1931 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - W.C. Sypert survey, 1913-1914 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Travis @ Lamar St. deeds, 1916-1930 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Valley Pipe Line Co., 1935-1948 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Texas and Louisiana land, 1935 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Rice, Palmer, Corsicana & Mexia, Texas, 1907-1909 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Calcasieu Parish, LA (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Houston, 1907-1909 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Lampasas County, TX, 1915 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Montgomery County, TX, Boy Scout camp, 1930 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Montgomery County, TX, mineral leases, 1918-1935 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Navarro County, TX, 1914 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Orange County, TX, 1911-1912 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - San Antonio, TX, 1908 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - St. James Hotel, San Antonio, TX, 1907-1908 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Southern Production Co., 1941-1942 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Tyler County, TX, S.F. Farish, 1932 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Tyler County, TX, Kirby Lumber Co., 1928, 1936 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Dallas County, TX, 1897-1915 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Timber land, LA, Frederick Shutts correspondence, 1912-1920 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Harris County, TX
    - Reinerman survey-Washington Road lease (Camp Logan), 1917-1932 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Camp Logan golf course, 1925-1926 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Camp Logan first addition, 1930 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - City of Houston, 1919-1925 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - City of Houston, 6451 & 6511 Main St., 1939-1940 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - City of Houston, 509 Travis, 1909-1910 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - City of Houston, Dallas @ Fannin St., 1935 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Deeded to Harris County for widening Main St., 1909-1914 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Democratic National Convention property, 1928 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Drainage of Post Oak Road extension, 1936 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Encroachment on Institute property by Richmond Place, 1932-1934 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Emerson Building offices, 1925-1927 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Extension of Washington Road through Institute land, 1914-1920 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Fire plug on Main St., 1938-1939 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Flood control, 1936 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - General, 1922-1927 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Houston & Texas Central Railroad Co. and Institute property, 1908-1913 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - W.J. Hutchins and Institute property, 1907 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - City of Houston, Louisiana St. property correspondence, 1910-1914 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - City of Houston, Louisiana St. property correspondence, 1915-1927 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - City of Houston, Louisiana St. property lease contracts & plat, 1910-1923 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Branch T. Masterson and Institute property, 1907 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - City of Houston, Milam St. lighting, 1929-1930 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Lease, Celia Nevill, 1915 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - King E. Choate, oil & gas lease, 1932-1933 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Houston Golf Club, 1909-1910 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Olympia Candy Kitchen, 217 Main St. Houston, TX (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - Reinerman survey, 1910-1915 (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - Nichols Rice Cherry house, 1924 (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - Richmond Avenue, 1929-1933 (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - South End Land Co., 1919-1920 (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - Institute site, University Place Realty Co., 1927-1928 (Box 19, Folder 16)
    - Matteson-Southwest, Inc., 1936 (Box 19, Folder 17)
    - George P. Martin, Ye Olde College Inn, 1936 (Box 19, Folder 18)
    - Rice Institute vs. Texas & New Orleans Railroad Co., 1909-1917 (Box 19, Folder 19)
    - Various county property, 1918-1933 (Box 19, Folder 20)
  - Rice Institute buildings and grounds
    - Administration Building, 1910-1935 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Chemistry Lab, 1923-1925 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Cohen House, 1927-1930 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Co-operative Store, 1923 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Entrance gates, 1912 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Metal file cabinets, 1908-1910 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Field House/grandstand, 1920-1931 (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Grounds, 1910-1933 (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - License & inspection ordinance (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - Institute site, 1910-1923 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Mechanical Lab & Power House, 1910-1912 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Monument to founder, 1927-1930 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Physics Lab, 1913 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Power House, 1925 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Railroad spur, 1916-1920 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Residential halls, 1911-1928 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - Treatment of trees, 1925-1931 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - General bulidings, 1910-1925 (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - Rice Institute-held
    - Audits, 1929-1936, 1943 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Endowment Fund investments, 1950 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1923-1935 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Statement, 1932 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Harris County assessments, 1909-1933 (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - City and county appraisals, 1934 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Quit-claim deed to Farmers Gin Co., Thornton, Limestone County, TX, 1931 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Receipts/vouchers, 1911 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Rent collection receipts, 1904 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Specifications for Empire Electric Supply Co. building, 1924 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Specifications for 1209 Congress Ave. building, 1926 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Specifications for Brazos Valley Buick Co. building (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Property under mortgage tax payments, 1931-1933 (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - Capitol Hotel
    - Correspondence: WMR, 1897-1899 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Bank statement, 1897 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Bank statements, 1897-1898 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - Operation statements, 1897-1899 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Utility statements, 1896-1897 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Furniture & fixture inventory, 1899-1900 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Daily reports of receipts & disbursements, 1897-1899 (Box 25, Folder 1-6)
    - Payroll, mechanical department, 1896-1898 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Payroll, waiters, 1897 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Payroll, general, 1897 (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - Receipts for professional services on hotel annex, 1899 (Box 25, Folder 10)
  - Rice Hotel
    - Cancelled checks and receipts, 1907 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Furniture & fixtures, 1907-1908 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, general, 1907-1910 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Taxes, 1907-1937 (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Houston Hotel Association, 1915-1925 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Elevator, 1907-1908 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Jesse Jones, 1912-1914 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Leases, 1907-1910 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Labor, 1907 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Receipts, 1907-1908 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Structural repairs, 1906-1908 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Specifications, 1907-1908 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Utilities, 1907-1910 (Box 27, Folder 7)
  - Ranch lands
    - Bank statements, 1896-1901 (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
    - P.M. Granberry contract, 1900-1901 (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Ledgers (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Payroll, 1898-1900 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - South Texas Land Co., 1909 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Stock inventory, 1898 (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - George L. Porter & Co. Real Estate, 1907 (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - WMR account with B.F. Davis, 1897-1898 (Box 28, Folder 9)
  - Land grants
    - Obedience Smith survey, Houston, 1877-09-11 (Box 29)
      Conditions Governing Access
      These materials are open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
      Arrangement
      The papers are arranged in 10 series: Series I: President; Series II: Fellowships, Funds and Scholarships; Series III: Correspondence; Series IV: Financial; Series V: Property; Series VI: Rincon Field; Series VII: Rice Lumber Co.; Series VIII: Legal; Series IX: South Main Co.; Series X: Trustees
    - Grant to WMR/Houston Tap & Brazoria Railroad Co., Lampasas Co. TX, 1870-06-14 (Box 29)
    - Grant to Ambrose P. Jordan, Tyler Co. TX, 1862-08-29 (Box 29)
    - Grant to John C. Donnelly, Harris Co. TX, 1849-10-25 (Box 29)
    - Grant to WMR/Houston Tap & Brazoria Railroad Co., Lampasas Co. TX, 1893-10-11 (Box 29)
    - Grant to J.S. & W.M. Rice, Tyler Co. TX, 1893-06-30 (Box 29)
    - Grant to Wesley Haigler, Robertson Co. TX, 1846-01-18 (Box 29)
    - Grant to George W. Smyth, Jasper Co. TX, 1852-03-01 (Box 29)
    - Grant to WMR/Houston Tap & Brazoria Railroad Co., Lampasas Co. TX, 1870-06-10 (Box 29)
    - Grant to WMR/Houston Tap & Brazoria Railroad Co., Lampasas Co. TX, 1870-06-11 (Box 29)
    - Grant to A.P. Jordan, Tyler Co. TX, 1917-01-23 (Box 29)
    - Grant to WMR/Houston Tap & Brazoria Railroad Co., Lampasas Co. TX, 1870-06-11 (Box 29)
    - Grant to Peter D. Moyer, Newton Co. TX, 1907-07-24 (Box 29)
    - Grant to International & Great Northern Railroad Co., Tyler Co. TX, 1878-02-14 (Box 29)
    - Grant to John O. Felps/Buffalo Bayou Brazos & Colorado Railroad Co., Tyler Co. TX, 1862-08-28 (Box 29)
    - Grant to Jesse Walling/Antonio Varga, Anderson Co. TX, 1849-06-08 (Box 29)
    - Grant to International & Great Northern Railroad Co., Tyler Co. TX, 1878-02-25 (Box 29)
    - Grant to International & Great Northern Railroad Co., Tyler Co. TX, 1878-02-27 (Box 29)
    - Grant to International & Great Northern Railroad Co., Tyler Co. TX, 1878-02-27 (Box 29)
    - Grant to International & Great Northern Railroad Co., Tyler Co. TX, 1878-02-15 (Box 29)
    - Grant to John T. Stark, Jr./William F. Tanner, Newton Co. TX, 1892-06-15 (Box 29)
    - Grant to John T. Stark, Jr./William F. Tanner, Newton Co. TX, 1876-12-19 (Box 29)
    - Grant to International & Great Northern Railroad Co., Tyler Co. TX, 1876-12-21 (Box 29)
    - Grant to International & Great Northern Railroad Co., Tyler Co. TX, 1917-04-12 (Box 29)
    - Grant to WMR/Houston Tap & Brazoria Railroad Co., Lampasas Co. TX, 1870-06-08 (Box 29)
    - Grant to WMR/Galveston & ? Co., Lampasas Co. TX, 1887-06-03 (Box 29)
    - Grant to WMR/Galveston & Brazoria Navigation Co., Lampasas Co. TX, 1887-03-15 (Box 29)
    - Grant to WMR/Galveston & Brazoria Navigation Co., Lampasas Co. TX, 1875-06-26 (Box 29)
    - Grant to WMR/Houston Tap & Brazoria Railroad Co., Lampasas Co. TX, 1875-08-12 (Box 29)
    - Grant to W.H. Smith, Jasper Co. TX, 1872-07-08 (Box 29)
    - Grant to W.H. Smith, Jasper Co. TX, 1891-08-29 (Box 29)
    - Grant to Andrew F. Smyth, Jasper Co. TX, 1851-02-20 (Box 29)
    - Grant to Surana Allen, Jasper Co. TX, 1848-08-19 (Box 29)
    - Grant to George W. Smyth, Jasper Co. TX, 1842-03-01 (Box 29)
    - Grant to George W. Smyth, Jasper Co. TX, 1891-12-11 (Box 29)
    - Grant to George W. Smyth, Jasper Co. TX, 1891-12-11 (Box 29)
    - Grant to Polly Youngblood, Newton Co. TX, 1849-01-09 (Box 29)
    - Grant to T.W., H.B., E.M. House/Day Land & Cattle Co., Harris Co. TX, 1892-10-25 (Box 29)
    - Grant to W.H. Smith, Jasper Co. TX, 1882-06-05 (Box 29)
    - Grant to W.B. Cline/BBB &C RR Co., Tyler Co. TX, 1876-02-16 (Box 29)
  - Blueprints, drawings